CURRICULUM VITAE

Amer Mohammed AL-Jamaeen

Personal Info

Nationality: Jordanian

Date of birth: 1984

Nationality: Jordanian

Resident in: Saudi Arabia

Marital status: Married

Mobile: +966563716410

E-mail: amer_jamaeen@hotmail.com
Blog: https://ajamaeen.blogspot.com

Iqama: Transferable

Summary

Software Architect with more than 12 years of extensive technical experience in large-scale enterprise software development, helping enterprises in their digital transformation journey from envisioning new possibilities to delivering solutions that result in targeted business outcomes and a great customer experience based on Microsoft platform (.Net & cloud computing), engage over the entire lifecycle of projects from pre-sales through delivery.

Responsible for handling complex architecture and design paradigms, and helping development teams choosing their tools, platforms, and coding standards.

Collaborating with the management, selecting the right development environment, interacting with stakeholders, and making sure projects are completed with high standards.

Technical experience in .Net technologies, with exposure to other platforms like BizTalk, SharePoint, CRM and Azure.

Experience in requirement analysis, project management, software architecture, design, Development and support. worked in different SDLC models, like Agile.

Education

Yarmouk University Irbid – Jordan: B.Sc. degree in computer information system, 2002-2006 GPA 85.5 % (Excellent).

High School, Scientific Stream: Graduated in August 2002.

Experience

[Feb / 2019 - Till Now]

Software Architect | Perfect Presentation (2P) | Riyadh

Collaborating with diverse range of technical architects, to help deliver multiple governmental projects.

Helping the company with its digital transformation, to support a modern technology stack, better agile process, and a mature design & architectural renovation.

Translate customer business requirements into integrated technical solutions, Responsible for the technology discussions, proposal and Participates in the development of responses to RFIs and RFPs.

Leading teams to develop custom products in telecommunication field to deliver high quality software. Designing solution, create and review high level design and low level design documents.

Providing direct support to the sales and presales in the development and execution of strategies for 2P.

Provide advanced solution knowledge and assist the local presales with qualifying customer technical needs, developing and presenting customer solutions and architecture roadmap, assisting with proposals and demos.

[Aug / 2015 - Feb /2019]

Technical Team Leader & Solution Designer | Netways | Riyadh

Provides leadership, managing and mentor for developers involved in the development.

Writing architectural documents based on business requirements, communicate architectural documents to clients and developers, working directly with chief technology officer (CTO) to meet business requirements and deliver high quality software. Analysis and modification of enterprise systems. Coding core software components, collaborate closely with backend developers, QA testers, support teams, business teams.

Designed and worked in governmental services targeted to serve businesses register, process, and build centralized consumers' products for reference and audits.

- Provided technical documents illustrating systems architecture, components design, and internal APIs.
- System Architecture & Component Design
- Research, proof of concepts, and team support.
- Implementation, Testing & Support.
- · Business and technical analysis.
- Lead technical teams in designing and developing multiple enterprise systems.
- Provided technical documents illustrating systems architecture, components design, and internal APIs.
- · Lead teams working in agility processes.

[Jun 2014 - Jul 2015]

SharePoint Consultant | FutureTech | Jeddah

Administer and maintain both the SharePoint and public web servers as well as the development of the sites. Install, configure, maintain, upgrade and manage SharePoint Servers. Configure service applications such as Search, Metadata, User Profile and Synchronization. Assign proper permission levels for all users of the site. Provide support and guidance to customer personnel who will maintain their own content for the various SharePoint sites. Provide training for new customer personnel on how to manage their SharePoint site on an as needed basis and during yearly refresher training.

Experience is gathering the requirements from the Business users. Design and Architecture of SharePoint applications, Configuration and deployment of SharePoint infrastructure and Farms. Search Configuration, SharePoint Services. Customization of SharePoint Document management, Portal site Strong experience in preparing the technical design documents (functional specifications)

[Oct 2011 - Jun 2014]

Senior SharePoint Developer, web developer, senior software developer | Council of Saudi

chambers Riyadh

Responsible for a wide variety of application development and support processes. Front-end, back-end and/or full-stack, web application development. Design, develop, and maintain custom components (master pages, workflows, user controls, web parts and server-side code, automates some tasks with PowerShell scripting). SharePoint implementation, customization, development, and architecture. Support, development, custom design, architecture and customer interactions of the SharePoint Environment.

Interfacing with clients to identify business requirements, design solutions, develop the solutions and support.

[Jun 2010 - Oct 2011]

Senior Software Engineer | Oger Systems | Riyadh

Participate in full software development lifecycle including design, coding, code reviews, unit test development, bug fixing. Design, develop and rapidly deliver software solutions. Lead all aspects of products implementation from requirements gathering, software development, testing, documentation, training, and implementation. Participate in planning by analyzing requirements, estimating work effort, performing demos and write technical documentation. Interact with clients to determine their requirements and needs. Resolve and troubleshoot problems and complex issues.

Apr 2008 - Jun 2010

Senior Software Engineer | Estarta Solutions | Jordan

Performing front-end, back-end and/or full-stack, web application development. Design, build, and maintain efficient, reusable, and reliable C# code .Troubleshoot technical issues in a variety of application environments. Translate business requirements and product specifications into components of complex,

loosely-coupled, distributed systems. Delivering elegant solutions for the largest enterprises on a global scale. Assist in development of technical documentation for software.

Mar 2007 - Apr 2008

Fresh Software Engineer | Generic Corp | Jordan

Developing, building and testing web application using asp.net (C#) and JavaScript.

Feb 2007 - Mar 2007

Teacher Assistant | Yarmouk University & National Information Center | Jordan

Teacher assistant in Yarmouk University & Teacher in National Information Center

Projects (Recently):

Yamamah Communication Platform (Feb 2019 - Dec 2020)

Telecommunication project to send millions of SMS and Voice messages per minute by integration with different operators, System has many services that interact within each other in loosely coupled way to achieve business functionality based on event-driven architecture.

Role: Solution Architect.

Recruitment Platform SaaS (Jan 2018 - Feb 2019)

Subscription based application to automate hiring processes built with a cloud inspired architecture, in to provide high availability and scalability, while serving a big load.

Technologies included: Azure Active directory (B2C) .Net core, MVC Razor, SQL Server.

Role: Solution Architect, System Architecture & Component Design and Research, proof of concepts, and team support.

Saudi Food & Drug Authority Unified System (Jan 2018 – Jan-2019)

Unified system enable different system components to be developed and evolved independently reducing coupling and facilitating future changes. System has many services that interact within each other in loosely coupled way to achieve business functionality based event-driven across microservices architecture.

Role: Solution Architect.

E-services portal for General Sports Authority Saudi Arabia (Jan 2017 – Jun 2017)

Manage the licenses of sport centers working inside the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in addition to club membership, election and voting application the proposed solution based on Microsoft Technology stack. Leveraging Dynamics CRM 2015 as the platform for managing and organizing relational business entities. Microsoft SharePoint 2013 used to deliver the user experience to external users. Microsoft Service Bus for Windows Server used to mediate and dispatch messages.

Role: Solution Architect & Team Leader.

Accreditation System (E-Services) For Saudi Council of Engineers (Aug 2015 – Jan 2016)

Automation of business processes related to the registration of engineer, accreditation of new engineer and the renewal of existing accreditation based on Microsoft Technology stack.

Event-driven architecture leveraging Dynamics CRM 2015 as the platform for managing and organizing relational business entities. Microsoft SharePoint 2013 used to deliver the user experience to external users. Microsoft Service Bus for Windows Server used to mediate and dispatch messages.

Role: Team Leader.

Saudi Council of Engineers Intranet Portal (Mar 2016 – May 2016)

Developing Intranet Portal for the council.

Role: Team Leader.

Saudi electricity company internet Portal (Jun 2014 – Jun 2015)

Developing Intranet Portal for the council.

Role: SharePoint consultant and senior .net developer.

Open source Projects

 Smart and dynamic asp.net mvc wizard for enterprise application built with object oriented best practices with high maintainability and extensibility in mind

Project Uri: https://github.com/ajamaeen/asp.net-mvc-wizard

Technical Skills

- Microsoft Azure (laaS & PaaS services)
- Azure Active Directory and cloud identity
- Scripting, automation, and infrastructure-as-code
- cloud configurations, migrations, patterns, and practices
- ASP.Net , ASP.Net Web API , ASP.NET MVC , ASP.NET MVC Core
- SharePoint Development & Configuration
- Windows Communication Foundation (WCF) & Windows workflow foundation
- Android Application Development
- Client Side (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery and Angular 2)
- BizTalk Server 2009
- Entity Framework & ADO.Net
- MS SQL Server
- Windows application and Windows Services
- Object Oriented Design
- Domain Driven Design
- Document the architecture and design of the solution (Technical Design Documents).
- Software Architecture (micro service & monolithic, layers, tiers)
- DevOps (CI, CD)
- TFS
- Agile and Disciplined Agile Software Processes.

Freelance Projects

 Adahi web control panel & Android App working for Riyadh Municipality used in Eid Al-Adha to add Adahi info offline and upload data to server when connected to internet, built in using ASP.NET Web API, asp.net MVC and native android SDK.

Certifications:

- Developing Microsoft Azure Solutions
- Developing ASP.NET MVC 4 Web Applications
- Core Solutions of Microsoft SharePoint Server 2013
- Advanced Solutions of Microsoft SharePoint Server 2013

Languages:

Arabic: native language

English: very Good